A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Peace and Social Justice Program (PSJ), Human Rights and International Cooperation (HRIC), Office Files of Mahnaz lspahani FA597
Rockefeller Archive Center
Franklin Thomas’s presidency, lasting until his retirement in 1995, was defined by a commitment to connect the Foundation’s US and international activities around a few key themes. These themes were addressed through grants that created private sector partnerships, enhanced support for local community groups, and enlarged initiatives to promote human rights, with special attention to women’s rights. Throughout Thomas’s tenure, Ford staff reinforced his special commitment to bolstering marginalized communities and broadening access to the law and educational opportunity. The Ford Foundation led the way in building the fields of international security studies, arms control, human rights, and governance. Moreover, in this period, Ford was innovative in drawing together the fields of international cooperation and human rights into one program.
Susan Berresford in her tenure as president from 1996-1997 continued and expanded the activities she helped initiate under Thomas. She and her colleagues increased support for the arts and established a variety of major international collaborative efforts implementing the concept of one foundation. Ford staff in this period drew on the Foundation’s time-tested grantmaking strategies (supporting individuals and new institutions as needed), while concentrating on under-addressed issues and underserved populations. With Berresford’s encouragement, Foundation staff explicitly took into account the new global context, increasing opportunities for inclusion of disadvantaged populations in all of their activities.
- Chronological Correspondence, 1991-2002; I
  - Shepard Forman Chrons, 1991-1996 (Box 1)
  - Mahnaz Ispahani (MZI) Chrons, Sep 1992-Jul 1993 (Box 1)
  - Mahnaz Ispahani (MZI) Memoranda, 1993-1994 (Box 1)
  - Mahnaz Ispahani (MZI) Chrons, Jul 1993-1994 (Box 1)
  - Mahnaz Ispahani (MZI) Chrons (A-M), 1995 (Box 1)
  - Mahnaz Ispahani (MZI) Chrons (Mc-Z), 1995 (Box 1)
  - Mahnaz Ispahani (MZI) E-mail, 1995 (Box 1)
  - Mahnaz Ispahani (MZI) Memoranda, 1995-1996 (Box 1)
  - Mahnaz Ispahani (MZI) Chrons, 1996 (Box 2)
  - Mahnaz Ispahani (MZI) Chrons (A-K), 1997 (Box 2)
  - Mahnaz Ispahani (MZI) Chrons (L-Z), 1997 (Box 2)
  - Mahnaz Ispahani (MZI) Chrons, 1998 (Box 2)
  - Mahnaz Ispahani (MZI) Chrons, 1999 (Box 2)
  - Mahnaz Ispahani (MZI) Chrons, 2000 (Box 2)
  - Mahnaz Ispahani (MZI) Chrons, 2001-January 2002 (Box 2)
- Consultants, 1993-2001; II
  - Anderlini, Sanam and Two Twelve, 2001 (Box 3)
  - Ashton, Sarah, 1994-1999 (Box 3)
  - Atwood, Brian, 1993 (Box 3)
  - Bukovansky, Mlada, 1993-2000 (Box 3)
  - Butegwa, Florence, 2000-2001 (Box 3)
  - Castaneda, Jorge, 1998 (Box 3)
  - Findlay, Matthew, 1994-1997 (Box 3)
  - Forman, Shep, [1996] (Box 3)
  - Friedman, Thomas L., 1999 (Box 3)
  - Gopinath, Meenakshi, 1999 (Box 3)
  - Higashi, Taryn, 1996-1997 (Box 3)
  - Hessini, Leila, 1995-1997 (Box 3)
  - Keary, Lisa, 1998 (Box 3)
  - Lindblom, Lance, 2000 (Box 3)
  - Luck, Ed -- UN Review, 2001 (Box 3)
  - Montes, Manuel F. (Butch), 1999-2000 (Box 3)
  - Peniston, Mary, 1997-1999 (Box 3)
  - Sen, Amartya, 1997 (Box 3)
  - Shaheed, Fareeda, 2001 (Box 3)
  - Sick, Gary, 1993 (Box 3)
  - Stern, Jessica, 1999 (Box 3)
  - Tendler, Judith, 1997 (Box 3)
  - Whitfield, Teresa, 2000-2001 (Box 3)
  - Wiseman, Geoffrey, 1993 (Box 3)
- Board of Trustees, 1995-2001; III
  - Board of Trustees Meeting, Mar 1995 (Box 4)
  - Board of Trustees, Dec 1995 (Box 4)
  - Board of Trustees, Mar 1996 (Box 4)
  - Board of Trustees, Jun 1996 (Box 4)
  - Board of Trustees Meeting, Jun 26, 1996 (Box 4)
  - Transition -- Portfolio Reviews, 1996 (Box 4)
  - Transition -- PEG Transition, 1996 (Box 4)
  - Transition -- Miscellaneous Memoranda, 1996 (Box 4)
  - Board of Trustees, Dec 1996 (Box 4)
  - Board of Trustees, Jun 1997 (Box 4)
  - Board of Trustees, Sep 1997 (Box 4)
  - Board of Trustees Presentation, Jan 1998 (Box 4)
  - Board of Trustees, Jan 1998 (Box 4)
  - Board of Trustees, May 1998 (Box 4)
  - Board of Trustees, Sep 1998 (Box 4)
  - Board of Trustees, Jan 1999 (Box 4)
  - Board of Trustees, May 1999 (Box 4)
  - Board of Trustees, Sep 1999 (Box 4)
  - Board of Trustees, Jan 2000 (Box 4)
  - Board of Trustees, May 23-24, 2000 (Box 4)
  - Board of Trustees, Sep 2000 (Box 4)
  - Board of Trustees, Jan 2001 (Box 4)
  - Board of Trustees, May 2001 (Box 4)
  - Board of Trustees, Sep 2001 (Box 4)
- Liason Grants, 1990-1998; IV
  - Liason Grants A-C, 1990-1998 (Box 5)
  - Liason Grants D-N, 1990-1998 (Box 5)
  - Liason Grants O-Z, 1990-1998 (Box 5)
- ICT Scholar in Residence, 1998-2001; V
  - Background Papers, 1998-2000 (Box 6)
  - CCMC, 1999 (Box 6)
  - CCMC, 2000 (Box 6)
  - Columbia (Box 6)
  - ICT Finalists -- Deibert, Ronald, 2001 (Box 6)
  - ICT Scholar Background Memoranda, 2000 (Box 6)
  - ICT Scholar -- Miscellaneous Memoranda and Background, 2000 (Box 6)
  - ICT Scholar -- Miscellaneous Memoranda, 200-2001 (Box 6)
  - Information Technology and International Cooperation, 1999-2000 (Box 6)
  - IT Background -- S. Neill, 2000 (Box 6)
  - Kumdr Paper and Contacts in India, Aug 28, 2000 (Box 6)
  - New Technologies and International Cooperation Meeting, Jul 11, 2001 (Box 6)
  - Technology, 1999 (Box 6)
- Meetings, 1992-2001; VI
  - IAP Retreat -- Swift River Inn, Oct 7-10, 1992 (Box 7)
  - IAP Worldwide Meeting -- Lisbon, Portugal, Nov 9-13, 1992 (Box 7)
  - Work File -- Lisbon Conference, Nov 9-13, 1992 (Box 7)
  - Lisbon Samples -- Correspondence, Agenda, 1992-1994 (Box 7)
  - Moscow Briefing Book, Sep 26-30, 1993 (Box 7)
  - Board of Trustees Overseas Program Review, Sep 26-Oct 2, 1993 (Box 7)
  - Board of Trustees Program Review -- Prague, Sep 26-Oct 2, 1993 (Box 7)
  - Budapest/Prague, Sep 26-Oct 2, 1993 (Box 7)
  - Varieties of Muslim Experience Conference -- Istanbul, Turkey, Jun 11-16, 1994 (Box 7)
  - Muslim Societies Meeting Briefing Book, Jun 11-16, 1994 (Box 7)
  - Varities of Muslim Experience -- Istanbul, Jun 11-16, 1994 (Box 7)
  - Muslim Societies Meeting -- Background and Final Report, Jun 1994 (Box 7)
  - Beijing Plus 5, 1995 (Box 8)
  - Beijing Conference -- Grant-related, 1995 (Box 8)
  - Beijing Conference -- Memoranda/Email, 1995 (Box 8)
  - Beijing Conference -- Platforms for Action, 1995 (Box 8)
  - Beijing Conference -- Traveling Material, 1995 (Box 8)
  - Bertelsmann Foundation Symposium -- Gutersloh, Germany, Apr 15-17, 1996 (Box 8)
  - Program Officer Orientation Meeting, Oct 25, 1996 (Box 8)
  - Peace Process, Strengthening the, Dec 12, 1996 (Box 8)
  - Peace Process Meetings, 1997 (Box 8)
  - Peace and Social Justice (PSJ) Staff Retreat, Jan 1997 (Box 8)
  - PSJ Meeting, Feb 24, 1997 (Box 8)
  - New Voices Meeting, Mar 10-11, 1997 (Box 8)
  - The US Role in the World: New Priorities Abroad and New Voices at Home -- New Voices Meeting Binder, Mar 10-11, 1997 (Box 8)
  - The US Role in the World: New Priorities Abroad and New Voices at Home -- New Voices Meeting, Mar 10-11, 1997 (Box 8)
  - The US Role in the World: New Priorities Abroad and New Voices at Home -- New Voices Judith Tendler Report, Aug 8, 1997 (Box 8)
  - The US Role in the World: New Priorities Abroad and New Voices at Home -- New Voices Correspondence, 1997 (Box 8)
  - The US Role in the World: New Priorities Abroad and New Voices at Home -- New Voices Meeting and Report -- Background, Mar 10-11, 1997 (Box 8)
  - Human Rights and International Cooperation (HRIC) Retreat, Sep 1997 (Box 8)
  - PSJ Retreat, Nov 12-13, 1997 (Box 8)
  - Istanbul Meeting -- Notes and Religion and Gender (R&G) RGAs, Jan 1998 (Box 8)
  - Ford Foundation -- Program Division Leadership Group, Feb 16-20, 1998 (Box 9)
  - Defining International Cooperation, Apr 6, 1998 (Box 9)
  - Peace and Social Justice (PSJ) Worldwide Meeting, May 1998 (Box 9)
  - Human Rights and International Cooperation (HRIC) Retreat, Oct 1-2, 1998 (Box 9)
  - PSJ Program Manager Workshop, Jan 4, 1999 (Box 9)
  - International Cooperation Brainstorming Meetings, Mar-Apr 1999 (Box 9)
  - Ford Foundation Human Rights Meeting, Oct 25-27, 1999 (Box 9)
  - International Cooperation Meeting, Mar 27-29, 2000 (Box 9)
  - International Cooperation Meeting Briefing Book and Report, Mar 27-29, 2000 (Box 9)
  - Ford Foundation -- Transitional Justice Meeting, Apr 6, 2000 (Box 9)
  - Gender in International Cooperation Meeting, May 8-9, 2000 (Box 9)
  - Women's Leadership and Gender in International Relationships Meeting (1/4), May 8-9, 2000 (Box 10)
  - Women's Leadership and Gender in International Relationships Meeting (2/4), May 8-9, 2000 (Box 10)
  - Women and Gender Meeting (3/4), May 8-9, 2000 (Box 10)
  - Gender Meeting -- Miscellaneous (4/4), May 8-9, 2000 (Box 10)
  - Peace and Social Justice (PSJ) Worldwide Meeting -- Krakow, Poland, Jun 3-9, 2000 (Box 10)
  - Program Division Leadership, Mar 5-9, 2001 (Box 10)
  - International Cooperation (IC) Meeting -- Shanghai, China, Dec 13-15, 2001 (Box 10)
- Organization Files, 1993-1999; VII
  - Academy for Educational Development, 1998 (Box 10)
  - Carnegie Endowment -- J. Matlock Review of Moscow Center, 1998 (Box 10)
  - Council on Foreign Relations (CFR) Study Group on US Economic Relations in Africa, 1997 (Box 10)
  - Council on Foreign Relations (CFR) -- US Foreign Policy and the Muslim World Study Group (Box 10)
  - Fulbright/Institute of International Education (IIE) (1/2), 1997-1999 (Box 10)
  - Fulbright/Institute of International Education (IIE) (2/2), 1999 (Box 10)
  - Inter-American Dialogue, 1993-1999 (Box 10)
  - Macarthur Foundation, 1993 (Box 10)
  - National Humanities Center -- Fulbright Study, Jun 26, 1997 (Box 10)
  - New York University -- Center on International Cooperation, 1998-1999 (Box 10)
  - Pacific Council on International Policy (retreat materials, etc), 1998 (Box 10)
  - Stimson Center, 1993-1998 (Box 10)
  - United Nations Development Program, 1996 (Box 10)
  - Women's Foreign Policy Group, 1993-1998 (Box 10)
- Regional Files, 1993-1999; VIII
  - Africa -- Grantmaking in, 1994-1999 (Box 11)
  - Africa -- Human Rights (regional), 1998 (Box 11)
  - African American Institutes, 1994 (Box 11)
  - Africa/Strategy -- the Salih Booker Report, 1993-1996 (Box 11)
  - Africa -- South Africa, 1993 (Box 11)
  - Africa -- Strategy Papers, 1993-1996 (Box 11)
  - Bosnia, 1993 (Box 11)
  - Central America -- General, 1993 (Box 11)
  - Central America -- Initiative Meeting, Sep 20, 1995 (Box 11)
  - Central America -- Initiative, 1993-1996 (Box 11)
  - Cuba Trip, Mar 25-26, 1993 (Box 11)
  - Haiti Meeting, Aug 5, 1993 (Box 11)
- Subject Files, IX
  - Affirmative Action Working Group, 1999 (Box 12)
  - Dash, Michelle, 1997 (Box 12)
  - Democratization, 1994 (Box 12)
  - Ford Foundation and the Media (news clippings), 1995-1996 (Box 12)
  - Ford Foundation Meetings/Memoranda -- Gener and Religion in International Affairs Meeting Notes, Jul 1996 (Box 12)
  - Ford Foundation Meetings/Memoranda -- Memoranda prepared by Elizabeth/Mayada/Mlada, 1992-1994 (Box 12)
  - Ford Foundation Meetings/Memoranda -- November 22 Follow-up Meeting, Nov 22, 1994 (Box 12)
  - Ford Foundation Meetings/Memoranda -- Religion and Gender (R&G) -- Muslim Societies Meeting Follow-up, Dec 18, 1995 (Box 12)
  - Ford Foundation -- Old Programs -- "South Asia", 1969-1993 (Box 12)
  - Individuals and Institutions with Special Interest in Religion and Gender -- Catholics for a Free Choice, Jun 13, 1996 (Box 12)
  - Individuals and Institutions with Special Interest in Religion and Gender -- Sisterhood is Global Institute, 1994-1995 (Box 12)
  - Individuals and Institutions with Special Interest in Religion and Gender -- Religion and Gender -- Muslim Women's League, 1995 (Box 12)
  - Individuals and Institutions with Special Interest in Religion and Gender -- DePaul University/Beverly McCloud -- Islam in America, 1994 (Box 12)
  - International Law Program Officer or Assistant Program Officer, 1992 (Box 12)
  - Israel -- West Bank Gaza Strip, 1999 (Box 12)
  - Kosovo File, Jun 1999 (Box 12)
  - Middle East Proposals -- Middle East Meetings, Jun 26, 1990 (Box 12)
  - Middle East Proposals -- Conference to Examine the 1967 Arab-Israeli War, 1990-1991 (Box 12)
  - Middle East Proposals -- Brookings -- Middle East Studies Program, 1991 (Box 12)
  - Migration and Security -- Energy and Security, 1997 (Box 13)
  - Minorities in International Affairs -- Council on Foreign Relations (CFR) Meeting, Apr 25, 1995 (Box 13)
  - Minorities in International Affairs -- Notes of the CFR Meeting, Apr 25, 1995 (Box 13)
  - Minorities in International Affairs -- Chronology of Work, Jun 30, 1995 (Box 13)
  - Minorities in International Affairs -- Distribution of Notes/Excerpts of CFR Meeting to Foundation Staff, Feb 21, 1996 (Box 13)
  - Minorities in International Affairs -- Drafts of Cover Letters and Memoranda re: Distribution of meeting notes, 1995 (Box 13)
  - Minorities in International Affairs -- Excerpts from the CFR Meeting -- Final Version, Apr 25, 1995 (Box 13)
  - Minorities in International Affairs -- Meeting Agenda/Invitation Letter, 1995 (Box 13)
  - Minorities in International Affairs -- Memorandum to Charlayne Hunter-Gault, Apr 22, 1995 (Box 13)
  - Minorities in International Affairs -- Letters to Participants Transmitting Notes, Dec 4, 1995 (Box 13)
  - Minorities in International Affairs -- Memorandum to Mahmaz Ispahani -- List of Issues, May 11, 1995 (Box 13)
  - Minorities in International Affairs -- Lunch Meeting with S. Bell-Rose, Aug 24, 1995 (Box 13)
  - Minorities in International Affairs -- Related Correspondence, 1992-1996 (Box 13)
  - Minorities in International Affairs -- Thank You Letter to Participants (Box 13)
  - Minorities in International Affairs -- CFR Meeting Recording [CASSETTE TAPES], Apr 25, 1995 (Box 13)
  - Overseas Development Council, 1993-1995 (Box 13)
  - Peace and Security, 1991 (Box 13)
  - Program Assistant Workshop (J. Jaffre), 1997-1999 (Box 13)
  - Program Assistantship, 1998-2000 (Box 13)
  - Program -- Program Assistants, 1996 (Box 13)
  - Program -- Joint Program Review, 1995 (Box 13)
  - Program -- Program Paper -- International Affairs, 1994-1995 (Box 13)
  - Program -- Program Review -- International Affairs, 1993 (Box 13)
  - Program -- Program Review -- International Affairs, 1994 (Box 13)
  - Public Policy and International Affairs (PPIA) -- Washington, Nov 15, 1996 (Box 14)
  - Public Policy and International Affairs (PPIA) -- Meetings, 1995-1996 (Box 14)
  - Public Policy and International Affairs (PPIA), 1996 (Box 14)
  - Public Policy and International Affairs (PPIA) -- Academy for Educational Development, 1999 (Box 14)
  - Religion and Gender (R&G) -- Muslim Voices -- Responses from Regional Offices, 1994-1995 (Box 14)
  - Religion and Gender (R&G) -- Muslim Voices -- Previous Ford Foundation Grants related to Muslim Societies, 1979-1994 (Box 14)
  - Religion and Gender (R&G) -- Muslim Voices -- Biennial Program Review -- Muslim Societies Initiative, Mar 21, 1995 (Box 14)
  - Religion and Gender (R&G) -- Muslim Voices -- Strengthening Muslim Women's Voices, Apr 18, 1995 (Box 14)
  - Religion and Gender (R&G) -- Film and Media -- Proposals Received, 1995 (Box 14)
  - Religion and Gender (R&G) -- Film and Media -- Women and Media, 1996 (Box 14)
  - Religion and Gender (R&G) -- Ongoing Activities, 1993-1995 (Box 14)
  - Religion Meetings with Education, Arts and Culture (EAC) -- Correspondence, 1996 (Box 14)
  - Religion Meetings with Education, Arts and Culture (EAC) -- Culture and Education, 1996 (Box 14)
  - Religion Meetings with Education, Arts and Culture (EAC) -- Culture and Education Reports, 1996 (Box 14)
  - Religion Meetings with Education, Arts and Culture (EAC) -- Culture and Religion Subgroups, 1996 (Box 14)
  - Religion Meetings with Education, Arts and Culture (EAC) -- EAC Transition, 1996 (Box 14)
  - Religion Meetings with Education, Arts and Culture (EAC) -- Muslim Experience Meeting, Jun 11-16, 1994 (Box 14)
  - Religion Meetings with Education, Arts and Culture (EAC) -- Tarrytown Meeting, Mar 4-5, 1996 (Box 14)
  - United Nations (UN) Related Material, 1991-1994 (Box 14)
  - Vietnam, 1993-1995 (Box 14)
  - Vietnam -- International Relations Program, 1994 (Box 14)
  - Vietnam -- Meeting with Vice-Minister, Apr 25, 1997 (Box 14)
  - Women -- Women's Program Forum -- Memoranda, 1992-1997 (Box 14)
  - Woodrow Wilson International Center for Scholars, 1991-1995 (Box 14)
  - Woodrow Wilson -- Minority Fellowships (Nancy Feller), 1995 (Box 14)
  - Woodrow Wilson International Center for Scholars -- Review of Organization and Management and Conference on Water and Conflict, 1997 (Box 14)